C. F. Voegelin Papers 1934-1970 Mss.Ms.Coll.68
American Philosophical Society
C. F. Voegelin Papers
1934-1970
Mss.Ms.Coll.68
American Philosophical Society
34.5 Linear feet
Trained as an anthropologist at Berkeley under A.L. Kroeber and Robert Lowie, Carl Voegelin spent the majority of his career as a structural linguist specializing in Algonquian languages, including Delaware, Potawatomi, Fox, Menominee, and Shawnee, and on the Seneca, Ojibwa (Chippewa), and Blackfoot (Siksika). His most significant contributions came through his studies of Delaware, Shawnee, and Hopi, but he is also credited with reviving the International Journal of American Linguistics after the death of its founder, Franz Boas, and with nurturing the program in anthropology at Indiana University, where he was on faculty from 1941 until his retirement in 1976. The Voegelin collection contains field notes, lexical files, notebooks, papers, correspondence, and other materials relating to Voegelin's work on Native American languages. The bulk of the collection concerns Delaware and Shawnee, but there is significant material for Blackfoot, Menominee, Ojibwa and Potawatomi, Seneca, and Penobscot. Notes on Turkish, kept during the Second World War, are also present. Among other important series in the collection are Voegelin's correspondence and notes concerning two of his major projects: the translation and interpretation of the Walam Olam and his study of Shawnee law. Correspondents include Leonard Bloomfield, Eli Lilly, and Morris Swadesh. A portion of the collection is indexed in Kendall (1982).
Voegelin, C.F. (Charles Frederick), 1906-1986
General note
Conservation note
During processing, the collection was re-foldered and re-housed in acid-free folders and boxes. Metal fasteners were removed and replaced with plastic clips when necessary. A separate listing of torn or severely deteriorated manuscripts and manuscripts that need to have glue and tape removed has been compiled by series and submitted to the Conservation Department.
All newspaper clippings were photocopied onto acid-free paper; the original clippings were then discarded. Other brittle or torn items were also photocopied, and when considered valuable, were retained.
Other Finding Aids note
Indexed in part in Daythal Kendall's A Supplement to A Guide to Manuscripts Relating to the American Indian in the Library of the American Philosophical Society (Philadelphia: APS, 1982)
Related Archival Materials note
The papers of Erminie Wheeler-Voegelin are housed at the Newberry Library.
Carl Voegelin appears as a correspondent in several APS collections, including the papers of Frank Speck, William N. Fenton.
Accruals note
The final accession of Voegelin Papers (16.5 linear feet), received in 1999, has not been inventoried.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Voegelin Papers were donated to the APS Library by C.F. Voegelin in 1979 (Accession #1979-650ms) and by F.M. Voegelin in 1987 (Accession #1987-1087ms). The earlier accession was partially processed under the call number "B/V86p," and described in Daythal Kendall's A Supplement to A Guide to Manuscripts Relating to the American Indian in the Library of the American Philosophical Society(Philadelphia: APS, 1982). The two accessions are now integrated and share the call number "Ms Coll. #68."
Scope and Contents note
The C. F. Voegelin Papers contain correspondence, manuscripts of published and unpublished works by Voegelin and others, research notes by Voegelin and others, and one photograph, which document Voegelin's career as an anthropologist and linguist.
The papers (45 boxes; 25.25 linear feet) are divided into seven series:
Series I. Correspondence 1936-1968 1 box;.5 linear feet
Series II. Card files 1930s-1960s 25 boxes; 14.75 linear feet
Series III. Works Written or Translated by Voegelin 1942-1968 10 boxes; 4.75 linear feet
Series IV. Works Written or Translated by Others 1836-1968 2 boxes; 1 linear foot
Series V. Research Notes 1925-1967 4 boxes; 1.75 linear feet
Series VI. Notebooks 1934, 1940-1941, n.d. 6 boxes; 3 linear feet
Series VII. Photograph 1936? 1 box; 1 folder
Series III, V. Oversized 1 folder; stored with oversized manuscripts in vault
Oversized materials follow the same series arrangement as noted above. Cross referencing to oversized material appears on the folders in the standard sized boxes. Reprints have been moved to the printed materials collection of the APS library. To retrieve reprints, consult the card catalog for printed materials. One sound recording, "The Buffalo Story," has also been removed from the collection and cataloged as Recording #190. Sound tape reels of Voegelin's field research are archived in the Archives of Traditional Music at Indiana University and are indexed in A Catalog of the C.F. and F.M. Voegelin Archives of the Languages of the World, a copy of which is available in the manuscripts department of the APS. An exception to this is section 1 of "Shawnee Law," the sound tape reel of which is held at the APS, while the reels for the remaining sections 2-12 are at Indiana University. Researchers interested in Native Americans of the Eastern United States, particularly Shawnee, should also consult the Newberry Library for the papers of Erminie Wheeler.
Biographical/Historical note
Charles (Carl) Frederick Voegelin was an anthropologist and structural linguist best known for his studies of Native American languages. He was born in New York on 17 January 1906, the son of Charles and Elizabeth Herbst-Sepilius Voegelin. After earning his undergraduate degree from Stanford University in 1927, Voegelin received his PhD in 1932 from University of California-Berkeley, where he was a student of anthropologists Robert Lowie and Alfred Kroeber. Between 1933 and 1935 he received fellowships from the National Research Council and the American Council of Learned Societies to pursue research as a post-doctoral fellow at Yale. In 1935, Voegelin was appointed Assistant Professor of Anthropology at DePauw University, where he remained until 1940. He also lectured at summer sessions of the Linguistic Institute held in Ann Arbor and Chapel Hill between 1938 and 1941.
Voegelin began his long association with Indiana University in 1941 as Associate Professor of Anthropology in the Department of History. In the Bloomington Faculty Council memorial resolution to Voegelin (Indiana University, Circular 820-87), James Vaughan and Paul Gebhard note that the position "came about in part because Eli Lilly wished to see a small group of anthropologists and linguists address themselves to some problems of Indiana prehistory." This team of researchers, which included Voegelin's first wife Erminie Wheeler-Voegelin, developed a new translation and interpretation of the "Walum Olam." Voegelin was named Department Chairman (1947-1966) and Professor of Anthropology in 1947 at Indiana University, when the Department of Anthropology was established at Indiana, and Professor of Linguistics in 1964. In 1967, Voegelin was honored with the title "Distinguished Professor of Anthropology and Professor of Linguistics;" he served in this capacity until 1976, when he continued as Professor Emeritus at Indiana University and, after 1978, as visiting scholar at the University of Hawaii.
Throughout his career, Voegelin made significant contributions to research and scholarship in his field. He authored several books, including Tubatulabal Texts (1935) and Tubatulabal Grammar (1935), Shawnee Stems and the Jacob P. Dunn Miami Dictionary (1938-1940), Hopi Domains (1957), Linguistics and Anthropology (1975), and Classification and Index of the World's Languages (1977). Numerous scientific articles by Voegelin have been published in Language, The American Anthropologist, and the International Journal of American Linguistics, a journal first edited by Franz Boas and edited by Voegelin from 1944 to 1980. Voegelin also initiated several new research ventures: the monograph series Indiana University Publications in Anthropology and Linguistics and the journal Anthropological Linguistics; a summer field station at Flagstaff, Arizona with the Museum of Northern Arizona; and the Indiana Archives of the Languages of the World. His activities in professional associations included serving as a member of the Executive Committee of the American Anthropological Association and as President of the Linguistic Society of America.
In recognition of his many achievements, the American Anthropological Association honored Voegelin with the Distinguished Service Award, and Indiana University awarded him an Honorary Doctor of Letters. Voegelin died on 22 May 1986, survived by his second wife and professional colleague, Florence Marie Robinett.
Bloomfield, Leonard, 1887-1949; Hamp, Eric P.; Hockett, Charles Francis; Hodge, C. T., (Carleton Taylor), 1917-1998; Kenneth L. Hale, (Kenneth Locke), 1934-2001; Lilly, Eli, 1885-1977; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967; Taylor, Douglas MacRae; Turner, Glen; Witthoft, John; Wonderly, William Lower; Algonquian Indians; Algonquian languages; Blackfoot language; Card files.; Chippewa language; Delaware language; Field notes.; Fox language; Gelatin silver prints; Indians of North America--Delaware; Indians of North America--Illinois; Indians of North America--Indiana; Indians of North America--Languages; Indians of North America--New England; Indians of North America--New Mexico; Indians of South America; Linguistics; Maps.; Menominee language; Nitrate negatives; Notebooks; Ojibwa language; Potawatomi language; Seneca language; Shawnee language; Siksika language; Walam Olum
- Series I. Correspondence, 1936-1968 (Box Series I: A-W)
  Scope and Contents note
  contains primarily manuscript letters from Voegelin's colleagues, who discuss topics of professional interest. With the exception of the files for Eli Lilly and Douglas MacRae Taylor, few files contain extensive correspondence. Some of Voegelin's correspondents include:
  Bloomfield, Leonard
  Hale, Kenneth
  Hamp, Eric
  Hockett, Charles F.
  Hodge, Carleton T.
  Lilly, Eli
  Swadesh, Morris
  Taylor, Douglas MacRae
  Turner, Glen
  Witthoft, John
  Wonderly, William L.
  Series I is arranged alphabetically by correspondent's name and then chronologically within each folder. When a correspondence file includes letters to a third party (i.e., not Voegelin), the name is indicated on the container list by using an indent under the folder title.
  In a similar fashion, cross-references indicate when a piece of correspondence was originally found with materials filed in another series. Unidentified correspondence has been filed as "Unidentified" and is arranged chronologically. Enclosed manuscripts have been removed from this series and placed in Series III or IV as appropriate, and a photocopy of the title page was filed with the original letter.
  - Adams, Sidney, 1966
  - Arduin
    -See Ser. I, Taylor, Douglas McRae
  - Bloomfield, Leonard, 1938-1941
  - Chao, Yuen R., 1952
  - Darnell, Regna, 1968
    -See also Ser. III-B, "Apex and Terminal Nodes..."
  - Hale, Kenneth L., 1966-1967
  - Hamp, Eric, [1967]
  - Herzog, George, 1949
  - Hockett, Charles F., 1941
  - Hodge, Carleton T., [1967]
  - Krueger, John R., 1967
  - Lane, George, 11 Aug. [1949]
    -See also Ser. V-A, South American and Other Latin American Languages
  - Lilly, Eli, 1936-1950
  - Lounsbury, Floyd, 1946, n.d.
  - G.&C. Merriam Company, 1957
    -See also Ser. III-B, American Indian Language
  - Miranda, Pierre, 1966
  - Pacifique, R.P., 1936
  - Pearson, Kenneth E., 1953
  - Quain, Fannie Dunn to Shell, Olive A., 1949-1950
    -See also Ser. V-A, Kraho
  - Rowe, John H., 1949
  - Seaman, John N., 1941
  - Seeber, Ed, 1968
  - Shell, Olive A., 1951
    -See also Ser. I, Quain, Fannie Dunn
    -See also Ser. V-A, Cashibo (Pano Family)
  - Siebert, Frank, 1939
  - Spindler, Louis, [1954]
  - Swadesh, Morris, 1937
  - Taylor, Douglas MacRae Arduin, 1948-1950
    -See also Ser. V-A, Carib
  - Tedlock, Dennis, 1968
    -See also Ser. III-B, Language and Culture
  - Traeger, George L., 1949
  - Turner, Glen, 1950
  - Unidentified, 1936-1968, n.d.
  - Voegelin, Florence M., n.d.
  - Wells, H.B., 1945
  - Witthoft, John, 1954, n.d.
    -See also Ser. III-B, Walam Olum-- ["Supplemental Studies"]
  - Wonderly, William L, 1949-1950, n.d.
- Series II. Card Files, 1930s-1960s
  General note
  Series II: Cardfiles
  contain primarily Native American vocabulary and grammar interspersed with texts and other field and research notes. Languages represented in this series are: 1 box of comparative Algonquian vocabulary and grammar; 2 boxes of Blackfoot; 5 boxes of Delaware, including 1 box of Munsee and 1 box of Walam Olum vocabulary, which is keyed to the Rafinesque translation; 1 box of Fox stems labeled "research assistant's notes from published sources"; 3 boxes of Menominee vocabulary collected by Slotkin (research assistant?); 6 boxes of Ojibwa, of which one box was collected by McGregor (research assistant?); 1 box of Seneca, Ojibwa and Penobscot; 4 boxes of Shawnee; and 1 box of Seneca. Arrangement in most boxes appears to be by word classes, i.e., according to stems, prefixes and suffixes. Card files have been left in the original order in which they were received, although metal fasteners and rubberbands have been removed. Folded items too large to remain in the cardfiles were removed and replaced with numbered photocopies. These originals were refiled in folders with the same title as the box from which they were removed, and the folders were placed in a standard-sized document box. Within each folder the originals are interleaved with sheets of paper; the sheet before each original bears a number that corresponds to the number of its photocopy.
  - Algonquian--Comparative (Box Series II: 1)
  - Blackfoot #1 (Box Series II: 2)
  - Blackfoot #2 (Box Series II: 3)
  - Delaware #1 (Box Series II: 4)
  - Delaware #2 (Box Series II: 5)
  - [Delaware] (Box Series II: 6)
  - Delaware--Munsee (Box Series II: 7)
  - Delaware-- Walam Olum (Box Series II: 8)
  - Fox (Box Series II: 9)
  - Menominee #1 (Box Series II: 10)
    Collected by Slotkin
  - Menominee #2 (Box Series II: 11)
  - Menominee #3 (Box Series II: 12)
  - Ojibwa #1 (Box Series II: 13)
    Collected by McGregor
  - Ojibwa #2 (Box Series II: 14)
  - Ojibwa #3 (Box Series II: 15)
  - Ojibwa #4 (Box Series II: 16)
  - Ojibwa #5 (Box Series II: 17)
  - Ojibwa #6 (Box Series II: 18)
  - Ojibwa, Seneca, Penobscot (Box Series II: 19)
  - Shawnee #1 (Box Series II: 20)
  - Shawnee #2 (Box Series II: 21)
  - Shawnee #3 (Box Series II: 22)
  - Shawnee #4 (Box Series II: 23)
  - Unidentified (Box Series II: 24)
  - Blackfoot #1 (Box Series II: Document Box: B-U)
  - Blackfoot #2
  - Delaware #2--Items #1-#58
  - Delaware #2--Items #59--133
  - [Delaware]
  - Delaware--Munsee
  - Delaware-- Walam Olum
  - Menominee #1
  - Menominee #3
  - Ojibwa #3
  - Ojibwa #4
  - Shawnee #2
  - Shawnee #4
  - Unidentified
- Series III. Works by Voegelin, 1942-1968
  contains handwritten and typed notes, outlines, and drafts of books, articles, and reviews. Notes and drafts of a particular manuscript are interfiled. Works co-authored with another individual are filed in this series, and the co-author is noted on the outside of the folder. Marginalia and bylines in Voegelin's field notes and manuscript drafts indicate that he often collaborated with Erminie Wheeler and, especially, Florence Robinette. The series is divided into two subseries: III-A, Works Translated by Voegelin and III-B, Works Authored by Voegelin.
  - Subseries III-A: Works Translated by Voegelin, 1942-1954
    Contains three Native American texts that were translated and/or linguistically analyzed by Voegelin and which served as the basis of a publication by Voegelin. The texts are titled "Shawnee Episodes," Shawnee Laws, and Walam Olum. Erminie Wheeler-Voegelin collaborated with Voegelin in the fieldwork upon which these works are based. "Shawnee Episodes" includes thirteen autobiographical sketches of informant Nancy Williams, which were published by Voegelin in 1953 in an article titled "From FL [From Language] to TL [Target Language], Autobiography of a Woman." Files contain handwritten notes and typescripts of Shawnee transcriptions and English translations of the episodes. The text is arranged in numerical order, i.e., episodes 1-13, in three folders.
    Shawnee Laws is, according to the introduction, a "semiformalized text setting forth...standards of conduct for human relationships and...the mutual obligations between men and supernaturals." The handwritten title page states that the Laws were collected in the field in notebooks (see Ser. VI, Shawnee #17-25) in 1934 and dictated onto 31 audiotapes in 1952. Files contain handwritten notes and typescripts of transcriptions and translations. Versions of the draft are arranged into sections, roughly following the organization set forth in the introduction: introduction, playback version, dictated version (transcription only), dictated version (translation only), dictated version (transcription with translation), and notes. Folder #1 of "Section 7--Notes" includes part of a draft for the published article titled "Shawnee Laws: Perceptual Statements for the Language and for the Content" by C. F. Voegelin, John F. Yegerlehner, and Florence M. Robinett.
    The last text in the subseries is Walam Olum, which is a record of the migration of the Lenape or Delaware Indians. Voegelin's translation of this work is used in Walam Olum or Red Score: The Migration Legend of the Lenni Lenape or Delaware Indians published by the Indiana Historical Society in 1954. Manuscript and typewritten notes and drafts for this publication are contained in folders titled Walam Olum--Voegelin Translation. Other materials filed here include pictographs, supplemental studies, and a verse translation by an unidentified author. Translations of the Walam Olum by Daniel G. Brinton and Constantine Rafinesque are filed in Series IV.
    - "Shawnee Episodes", [1953]; 5 Folders (Box Series IIIA: A - SHAWNEE EPISODES #3-1 - SHAWNEE LAWS: Section 2 #4)
    - Shawnee Laws: Section 1--Introduction, [1952]
    - Shawnee Laws: Section 2--Playback Version, [1952]
      - Folder #1-4
      - Folders #5-14 (Box Series IIIA: SHAWNEE LAWS: Section 2 #5-14)
      - Folders #15-22 (Box Series IIIA: SHAWNEE LAWS: Section 2 #15-22)
      - Folders #23-31 (Box Series IIIA: SHAWNEE LAWS: Section 2 #23 - SHAWNEE LAWS: Section 4)
    - Shawnee Laws: Section 3--Dictated Version (Transcription Only), [1952]
    - Shawnee Laws: Section 4--Dictated Version (Translation Only), [1952]
      Includes photocopy
    - Shawnee Laws: Section 5--Dictated Version (Transcription With Translation) (Box Series IIIA: SHAWNEE LAWS: Section 5 - WALAM OLUM--VOEGELIN...#2)
    - Shawnee Laws: Section 5--Dictated Version (Transcription With Translation), [1952]; 6 Folders
      Original (Fragile. Researchers must use photocopy.)
    - Shawnee Laws: Section 6--Notes, [1952]; 2 Folders
    - Walam Olum-- Pictographs, n.d.
    - Walam Olum--["Supplemental Studies"]-- with John Witthoft, [1954]
    - Walam Olum-- Verse Version, n.d.
    - Walam Olum-- Voegelin Translation
      - Folder #1, 1946
        -See also Oversized
      - Folder #2, 1942, 1946
      - Folder #3, n.d. (Box Series IIIA: WALAM OLUM VOEGELIN...#3-4)
      - Folder #4, [1948]
  - Subseries III-B: Works Authored by Voegelin, 1949-1968
    Series III-B: Works Authored by Voegelin
    Contains hand- and typewritten notes, outlines, and drafts of books, journal articles, lectures, grammars, and a book review by Voegelin. Arrangement is alphabetical by title. Two of the works in this subseries, American Indian Language and Language and Culture (also titled Language and Culture in Society and Language and Culture: From Ethnolinguistics and Sociolinguistics to Cognitive Ethnography) were intended for publication as books. Because large sections, including tables of contents and chapter and section titles, of these two manuscripts were heavily revised, drafts have been kept in the original order in which they were received. Occasionally, a section of one of the books appears to be marked for separate publication; in this event, the section is filed separately in subseries III-B under its distinct title and cross-referenced either to Language and Culture or American Indian Language.
    - American Indian Language, 7 Folders (Box Series IIIB: AM-AP)
    - "Anthropological Linguistics and Translation"
    - "Apex and Terminal Nodes in the Linguist's Taxonomy of Genetically Related Languages", 1968; 2 Folders
    - "Basic Shawnee", n.d. (Box Series IIIB: B - Language and Culture #4)
    - "Black Carib Morphology", [ca. 1949]
      -See also Ser. I, Taylor, Douglas MacRae
      -See also Ser. IV, Taylor, Douglas MacRae
    - "Central American Carib II: Morphology of the Verb"--With Douglas MacRae Taylor, [ca. 1949]
    - "Cotraditional and New-Wine-Into-Old-Bottles Course of Linguistic History"
    - "Cross-Cultural Typologies and Folk Taxonomies"--With F.M. Voegelin
    - [Delaware Grammar], n.d.
    - "Ethnological Research Opportunities in Colombia", n.d.
    - Field Linguistics: A Guide to Linguistic Field Work by William J. Samarin--Review, [1967?]
    - Language and Culture, [ca. 1967]
      - Folders #1-4
      - Folders #5-12 (Box Series IIIB: Language and Culture #5-12)
    - ["Language and Linguistics"]--Lecture Notes (Box Series IIIB: Language and Linguistics - W)
    - "Linguistically Marked Distinctions in Meaning", 1950
      -See also Ser. III-B, American Indian Languages
    - "The Linguist's Image of Language", [ca. 1967]
    - "Living Language Families", n.d.
      -See also Oversize
    - "Major Morpheme Classes", n.d.
    - "Notes and Queries on the Nature of Language", [1952]
    - "Notes on Warao Verbs", n.d.
    - "On the Probability of Autonomous Linguistics Converging with Hyphenated Linguistics", n.d.
    - ["Papago and Hopi"]
    - "Peopling of the New World (South America After North America)"
      -See also Ser. IV, Murdock, George, "Maps for South America"
    - "Professions of Faith: Three Addenda", 1943
    - "Seneca I"--with W.D. Preston, n.d.
    - "Sounds"
      See also Ser. III-B, Language and Culture
    - ["Shawnee Morphology"], n.d.
    - "Typology of Information for Deciphering Writing"--With F.M. Voegelin, n.d.
    - "The Weltanshaung Theory in Relation to Ethnoscience Procedures", [ca. 1967]
      -See Ser. III-B, Language and Culture
- Series IV. Works by Others, 1836-1968
  contains handwritten, typed, and carbon copies of theses, grant proposals, working papers, lectures, and maps. Translations of Walam Olum other than Voegelin's are filed here. Works are arranged alphabetically, first by author and then by title. Only one author, Douglas MacRae Taylor, has more than one work in this series.
  - "Iran", n.d.; Banayan, A. (Box Series IV: B - FI)
  - "The Walam Olum, or Red Score of the Lenape", 1885; Brinton, Daniel Garrison, 1837-1899
    -See also Ser. III-A, Walam Olum
  - "Style Variation in English Verse"-- Grant Proposal, 1966; Brown, Augustus F.
  - "Becoming a Bilingual"--Working Paper, Mar. 1968; Ervin-Tripp, Susan
  - "The Case for Case", [1967]; 2 Folders; Fillmore, Charles J.
  - "Materials for Phonetic Instruction", 1952; Foreign Service Institute (Box Series IV: FO-WO)
  - "Translation Procedures", n.d.; Fortune, David L.
  - "Phonemes of North Pame", n.d.; Gibson, Lorna F.
    -See also Ser. V-A, North Pame
  - "A Morphological Analysis of Cuicateco Words", Jan. 1954; Goetz, Joan Elisabeth
    -See also Ser. V-A, Cuicateco
  - "Two Fundamental Problems in Phonemics", 1949; Hockett, Charles Francis
  - "Fallacies in the History of Linguistics and the Appraisal of the Early 19th Century", Hoenigswald, Henry M.